Chunk two Okay we're back and
you just dropped a bombshell a drug to fix a money problem
Walk me through it So picture the 1830s The British absolutely
loved Chinese tea and silk and porcelain good stuff
But here's the catch China didn't really want to buy much from Britain so Britain
had to pay for all this tea in silver Silver was flowing out of Britain
into China fast So Britain's got a trade problem Spending
more than they earn Exactly So Britain's answer grow
opium in India which Britain already ruled The East India
Company grew it by the ton and smuggled it into China Wait
smuggled So Britain was selling a drug that China had made illegal
Illegal and devastating The thing is opium addiction spread
like wildfire and suddenly the money didn't flow one way anymore It
reversed Chinese people were paying Britain for the opium And Britain
took those silver coins and bought tea with them The trade balanced but
it destroyed China to do it And China's government tried
to stop it That's the famous story right The emperor was furious when he found out his own
people even his own officials were smoking opium Yes So he
sent a guy named Lin Zexu and Lin did the most dramatic thing imaginable
He took all the British opium and destroyed it tons of it right
into the sea And I bet Britain did not take that well Nope
Britain used it as the perfect excuse They said you destroyed our property
This is an attack on free trade And they sent the navy That's the first
Opium War And China lost right Completely
The Treaty of Nanking in 1842 China had
to open five ports pay a huge amount of money and hand over the island of Hong Kong to Britain And
that was just the first round Now listen again Okay we're back And
you just dropped A bombshell a drug to fix a money problem
Walk me through it So picture the 1830s The British absolutely
loved Chinese tea and silk and porcelain good stuff
But here's the catch China didn't really want to buy much from Britain so Britain
had to pay for all this tea in silver Silver was flowing out of Britain
into China fast So Britain's got a trade problem They're spending
more than they earn Exactly So Britain's answer grow
opium In India which Britain already ruled the East India Company
grew it by the ton and smuggled it into China Wait smuggled
So Britain was selling a drug that China had made illegal Illegal and devastating
The thing is opium addiction spread like wildfire and suddenly the
money didn't flow one way anymore It reversed Chinese people
were paying Britain for the opium and Britain took those silver coins and bought
tea with them The trade balanced but it destroyed China And China's
government tried to stop it That's the famous story right The emperor was
furious when he found out his own people even his own officials were smoking opium Yes
So he sent a guy named Lin Zexu and Lin did the most dramatic thing
imaginable He took all the British opium and destroyed it tons of it
right into the sea And I bet Britain did not take that well Nope
Britain used it as the perfect excuse They said You destroyed our property
This is an attack on free trade and they sent the navy That's
the first Opium War and China lost right Completely
The Treaty of Nanking in 1842 China had to open five ports
pay a huge amount of money and hand over the island of Hong Kong to Britain and
that was just the first round